Spiro, Eugen; Papers ger086
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
- Writings of Eugen Spiro, 1932-1964; Undated; 3; 8 file folders
  This series consists of typescripts of essays as well as several early stories by Spiro.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - "Tante Rosie."Clipping, Undated (Box 2 (3-Writings of Eugen Spiro), Folder 5)
  - "Ein neuer Spiegel, der kein Spiegelbild zeigt". Clipping, 1932 (Box 2 (3-Writings of Eugen Spiro), Folder 6)
  - "The double-mirror", ca. 1954; typescript of English text (Box 2 (3-Writings of Eugen Spiro), Folder 6)
  - "Als ich Albert Einstein malte", 1955 May 9; typescript, newspaper clipping (Box 2 (3-Writings of Eugen Spiro), Folder 7)
    also related correspondence.
  - "Die Vier (Ein fragmentarische Pessacherzählung)". Unpublished, 1961 April 1; typescript (Box 2 (3-Writings of Eugen Spiro), Folder 8)
  - "Weg der Menschlichkeit". Unpublished, 1962 April 18; typescript (Box 2 (3-Writings of Eugen Spiro), Folder 9)
  - "Wie ich den Raub der Mona Lisa entdeckte", 1963 February 15; typescript, newspaper clipping (Box 2 (3-Writings of Eugen Spiro), Folder 10)
  - "Selbstbetrachtung (Selbstportrait?)", ca. 1964; typescript (Box 2 (3-Writings of Eugen Spiro), Folder 11)
    English version, entitled "Looking at Myself ..." Typescript.
  - "Edouard Manet's first 'plein air' painting", Undated; typescript, unpublished (Box 2 (3-Writings of Eugen Spiro), Folder 12)
- Newspaper clippings pertaining to Spiro and his artwork; catalogs of exhibits, 1903-1978; 4; 16 file folders
  This series consists of articles in newspapers and magazines about Spiro, reviews of exhibits of his work, as well as catalogs of exhibits.
  - Clippings, 1903-1978 (Box 2 (4-Newspaper clippings pertaining to Spiro and his ar), Folder 13)
    Includes clippings about his arrival in the U.S.
  - Catalogs, clippings concerning Spiro exhibit at the Galerie St. Etienne, 1943 February-1943 March (Box 2 (4-Newspaper clippings pertaining to Spiro and his ar), Folder 14)
  - Catalogs of Spiro exhibit, Galerie St. Etienne, 1945 January-1945 February (Box 2 (4-Newspaper clippings pertaining to Spiro and his ar), Folder 15)
  - Clippings of Spiro exhibits, 1952-1973 (Box 2 (4-Newspaper clippings pertaining to Spiro and his ar), Folder 16)
  - Clippings concerning Spiro's teaching, 1952-1956 (Box 2 (4-Newspaper clippings pertaining to Spiro and his ar), Folder 17)
  - Catalogs of Spiro / James N. Rosenberg exhibit, Galerie St. Etienne, 1954 May (Box 2 (4-Newspaper clippings pertaining to Spiro and his ar), Folder 18)
  - Clippings, catalog of Spiro exhibit, Galerie Gurlit, 1957 August (Box 2 (4-Newspaper clippings pertaining to Spiro and his ar), Folder 19)
  - Clippings, 85th birthday, 1959 (Box 2 (4-Newspaper clippings pertaining to Spiro and his ar), Folder 20)
  - Catalogs, clippings of Spiro exhibit, Galerie St. Etienne, 1960 February 6 (Box 2 (4-Newspaper clippings pertaining to Spiro and his ar), Folder 21)
  - Catalogs, materials concerning Spiro exhibit, Galerie St. Etienne, 1964 April (Box 2 (4-Newspaper clippings pertaining to Spiro and his ar), Folder 22)
  - Clippings, articles concerning Spiro's 90th birthday, 1964 (Box 2 (4-Newspaper clippings pertaining to Spiro and his ar), Folder 23)
  - Copies of Self-portrait (1964) and facsimile thank you note sent to friends (Box 2 (4-Newspaper clippings pertaining to Spiro and his ar), Folder 24)
  - Catalogs of Berlin Museum exhibit, 1969 (Box 2 (4-Newspaper clippings pertaining to Spiro and his ar), Folder 25)
  - Clippings, articles concerning Spiro's 95th birthday, 1969 (Box 2 (4-Newspaper clippings pertaining to Spiro and his ar), Folder 26)
  - Obituaries, memorial addresses, clippings, 1972 (Box 2 (4-Newspaper clippings pertaining to Spiro and his ar), Folder 27)
  - Catalogs, materials concerning posthumous Spiro exhibits, Galerie von Abercron, 1978 January 28; 1978 September 13 (Box 2 (4-Newspaper clippings pertaining to Spiro and his ar), Folder 28)
- Reproductions and photographs of Eugen Spiro's artwork, 1905-1979; 5; 8 file folders
  This series contains printed reproductions of Spiro's paintings in magazines and newspapers, as well as copies of early magazine covers illustrated by Spiro. In addition, the series contains photographs (mostly dated) of Spiro's portraits, landscape paintings and sketches of prominent musicians. Additional photographs of Spiro's artwork are located in the correspondence files of their owners (Series 1).
  - Reproductions of early artwork in magazines, magazine covers, etc., 1916-1930 (Box 3 (5-Reproductions and photographs of Eugen Spiro's art), Folder 1)
  - Photographs of Albert Einstein portraits, Undated (Box 3 (5-Reproductions and photographs of Eugen Spiro's art), Folder 2)
  - Reproductions of Einstein portraits, 1943-1979 (Box 3 (5-Reproductions and photographs of Eugen Spiro's art), Folder 3)
  - Reproductions of Spiro sketch entitled "Round trip", 1949-1950 (Box 3 (5-Reproductions and photographs of Eugen Spiro's art), Folder 4)
  - Reproductions of artwork in magazines, 1953-1967 (Box 3 (5-Reproductions and photographs of Eugen Spiro's art), Folder 5)
  - Photographs of Spiro's prophet series, newspaper clippings, 1960-1961 (Box 3 (5-Reproductions and photographs of Eugen Spiro's art), Folder 6)
  - Reproductions of Spiro's prophet series in magazines, etc., 1960-1961 (Box 3 (5-Reproductions and photographs of Eugen Spiro's art), Folder 7)
  - Photographs of Spiro's artwork, 1905-1962; Undated (Box 3 (5-Reproductions and photographs of Eugen Spiro's art), Folder 8)
- Photographs of Eugen Spiro, Spiro family and friends, 1941-1978; Undated; 6; 20 file folders
  This series consists primarily of snapshot photographs of Eugen and Lilly Spiro, their friends and family members, including vacation photos and candid photos of Spiro's summer teaching classes.
  - Photos, early and ca. 1941-1943 (Box 3 (6-Photographs of Eugen Spiro, Spiro family and frien), Folder 9)
  - Old passport photos, Eugen and Lilly Spiro, Undated (Box 3 (6-Photographs of Eugen Spiro, Spiro family and frien), Folder 10)
  - Callicoon, 1948 (Box 3 (6-Photographs of Eugen Spiro, Spiro family and frien), Folder 11)
  - Lawrence Painting Group, 1948-1957 (Box 3 (6-Photographs of Eugen Spiro, Spiro family and frien), Folder 12)
  - Postcards, 1947 Summer; 1954 Summer; 1959 Summer (Box 3 (6-Photographs of Eugen Spiro, Spiro family and frien), Folder 13)
  - Teaching, Elizabethtown, 1949-1952; 1955 (Box 3 (6-Photographs of Eugen Spiro, Spiro family and frien), Folder 14)
  - Teaching, Hanover, NH, 1953 (Box 3 (6-Photographs of Eugen Spiro, Spiro family and frien), Folder 14)
  - Photograph, 1954 Summer (Box 3 (6-Photographs of Eugen Spiro, Spiro family and frien), Folder 15)
  - Kennebunkport, ME, 1955 Summer (Box 3 (6-Photographs of Eugen Spiro, Spiro family and frien), Folder 16)
  - Europe, 1956 June (Box 3 (6-Photographs of Eugen Spiro, Spiro family and frien), Folder 17)
  - South America, 1956 October (Box 3 (6-Photographs of Eugen Spiro, Spiro family and frien), Folder 18)
  - Orta, Italy, 1958 (Box 3 (6-Photographs of Eugen Spiro, Spiro family and frien), Folder 19)
  - 85th birthday, 1959 (Box 3 (6-Photographs of Eugen Spiro, Spiro family and frien), Folder 20)
  - Denmark, 1960 (Box 3 (6-Photographs of Eugen Spiro, Spiro family and frien), Folder 21)
  - Photograph, 1965 June (Box 3 (6-Photographs of Eugen Spiro, Spiro family and frien), Folder 22)
  - Snapshots, 1968 (Box 3 (6-Photographs of Eugen Spiro, Spiro family and frien), Folder 23)
  - Slides, ca. 1970 (Box 3 (6-Photographs of Eugen Spiro, Spiro family and frien), Folder 24)
  - Friends: G. R. Treviranus & family, Undated (Box 3 (6-Photographs of Eugen Spiro, Spiro family and frien), Folder 25)
  - Friends, Undated (Box 3 (6-Photographs of Eugen Spiro, Spiro family and frien), Folder 26)
  - Friends, 1961-1970 (Box 3 (6-Photographs of Eugen Spiro, Spiro family and frien), Folder 27)
  - Exhibition openings, 1954; 1960; 1978 (Box 3 (6-Photographs of Eugen Spiro, Spiro family and frien), Folder 28)
- Miscellaneous materials, Undated; 7; 8 file folders
  This series contains copies of original Spiro holiday cards, memorabilia, and materials concerning subjects of interest.
  - Original Spiro Christmas cards, 1950-1965 (Box 3 (7-Miscellaneous materials), Folder 29)
  - Balthus. Magazine articles about, Undated (Box 3 (7-Miscellaneous materials), Folder 30)
  - Loewi, Otto. Publications, Undated (Box 3 (7-Miscellaneous materials), Folder 31)
  - Memorabilia, Undated (Box 3 (7-Miscellaneous materials), Folder 32)
  - Polgar, Alfred. "Cera", Undated; typescript 3 p. (Box 3 (7-Miscellaneous materials), Folder 33)
  - Scheyer, Ernst. Publications, Undated (Box 3 (7-Miscellaneous materials), Folder 34)
  - Miscellaneous materials, Undated (Box 3 (7-Miscellaneous materials), Folder 35-36)